<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/document.dtd"[
<!ENTITY done-c SYSTEM "DONE">
<!ENTITY status-c SYSTEM "STATUS">
<!ENTITY history-c SYSTEM "history.xml">]>

<!--
 * Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->
<s1 title="What's New in this Release">
<p>Release notes for &xslt4c-current;</p>
 <ul>
  <li><link anchor="status">Status</link></li>
  <li><link anchor="contact">Getting in touch</link></li>
  <li><link anchor="history">History of software changes</link></li>  
 </ul>
<anchor name="status"/>
<s2 title="Status">
  <ul>
    <li><link anchor="done">Changes for &xslt4c; version 1.10</link></li>
    <li><link anchor="bugs">Bug reporting</link></li>    
    <li><link anchor="xml4c">Version of &xml4c; to use</link></li>
    <li><link anchor="to-do">To-do tasks for future &xslt4c; releases</link></li>
  </ul>

<anchor name="done"/>
<s3 title="Changes for &xslt4c; version 1.10">
<p>Major updates since version 1.9 include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Support for XML 1.1 and Namespaces in XML 1.1.</li>
  <li>Added support for IBM XLC 7.0 compiler on Linux.</li>
  <li>Improved and stabilized C pluggable memory management functionality.</li> 
  <li>Various improvements in Xalan XML serializers for better performance and stability.</li>
  <li>Upgrade from Xerces-C 2.6 to Xerces-C 2.7.</li>
  <li><link anchor="bugfixes">Bugs fixed in this release</link>.</li>
 </ul>  
</s3>  

<anchor name="bugfixes"/>
<s2 title="Bugs Fixed in this Release">
<p>The bugs fixed in this release include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>XALANC-115: Need to catch use of variables in xsl:key attributes </li>
  <li>XALANC-540: XPath absolute location path does not work when the context node was obtained from a result tree fragment through exsl:node-set() </li>
  <li>XALANC-544: Assert failure, then crash, during "variable undefined" error recovery in certain circumstances. </li>
  <li>XALANC-543: Crash when calling a template that wrongly uses xsl:with-param instead of xsl:param to declare its parameter. </li>
  <li>XALANC-539: XalanMap needs to compact buckets to prevent long search times and ever-increasing memory usage. </li>
  <li>XALANC-542: XalanDocumentFragmentXNodeSetBaseProxy::dereferenced() is not implemented properly </li>
  <li>XALANC-538: Better handling for non-existent node test </li>
  <li>XALANC-541: Fixes for zOS build </li>
  <li>XALANC-455: Problem when releasing InputSource obtained through an EntityResolver </li>
  <li>XALANC-538: Better handling for non-existent node test </li>
  <li>XALANC-535: If an error/warning message contains not-displayable character for the local encoding , no message is shown at all </li>
  <li>XALANC-532: FormatterToXMLUnicode does not serialize UTF-8 </li>
  <li>XALANC-536: ElemNumber uses extra temporary strings </li>
  <li>XALANC-537: XalanC source code quotes incorrectly license protected documents </li>
  <li>XALANC-526: Use of undefined stricmp breaks compilation on Linux </li>
  <li>XALANC-513: ICUFormatNumberFunctor has some MemoryManager issues </li>
  <li>XALANC-507: Safety improvements for XalanVector::insert() </li>
  <li>XALANC-506: Remove references to stlport directory in Makefile.incl.in </li>
  <li>XALANC-505: DirectoryEnumerator.hpp will not build on Solaris 10 with Sun Workshop 10 </li>
  <li>XALANC-502: XalanDOMStringCache has initializer list out of order </li>
  <li>XALANC-501: Creation of comments and PIs needs to detect illegal values </li>
  <li>XALANC-500: Remove old "diagnostic" output from StylesheetRoot and XSLTEngineImpl </li>
  <li>XALANC-497: Local variables or parameters in EXSLT-functions are interpreted as global </li>
  <li>XALANC-496: Glitches in header files </li>
  <li>XALANC-493: Problem with XALAN_STATIC_CHECK on HP-UX IA64 </li>
  <li>XALANC-492: Various pluggable memory management bugs. </li>
  <li>XALANC-490: XalanFileReporter is inconsistent in its usage of pluggable memory management </li>
  <li>XALANC-489: XalanMemMgrs has a thread-safety issue </li>
  <li>XALANC-488: XSLTInputSource does not support pluggable memory management </li>
  <li>XALANC-487: URISupport does not provide explicit MemoryManager </li>
  <li>XALANC-485: GCC warns about order of members in initializer list </li>
  <li>XALANC-484: Remove compiler warnings about placement delete for HP's aCC compiler </li>
  <li>XALANC-483: XercesParserLiaison does not create Xerces-C DOM instances with namespaces support enabled. </li>
  <li>XALANC-482: Remove compiler warnings </li>
  <li>XALANC-470: runConfigure does not pass link options to Makefile for AIX platform </li>
  <li>XALANC-465: Add alt tag to footer.html page under html/apiDocs tree. </li>
  <li>XALANC-463: Transforming an XML DOM document encapsulated within an XercesDOMWrapperParsedSource object triggers an invalid heap pointer exception if XSL opens other XML document with 'document()' function. </li>
  <li>XALANC-460: Linux/xlC port </li>
  <li>XALANC-448: TestXSLT/process.cpp compilation fails, interface broken in FormatterToText.hpp </li>
  <li>XALANC-445: generate-id() inserts periods into name which limits usage </li>
</ul>
</s2>

<anchor name="bugs"/>
<s3 title="Bug reporting">
<p>All known &xslt4c; bugs are listed in <resource-ref idref="jira"/>. For a list of open bugs with links to each bug
   report, see <resource-ref idref="buglist"/>. If you find a new bug, please enter a XalanC bug report in this
   database.</p>
<note>Before you can enter your first bug report, you must submit your email address to JIRA and receive a password.</note> 
<p>We strongly encourage you write patches for problems you find and submit them to
   xalan-dev@xml.apache.org. We review the patches we receive to make sure they do not break something else, and (assuming they 
   do not) include them in our next release. In the interest of fixing bugs, adding enhancements, and addressing outstanding design
   issues, we sincerely want (and need!) your active participation in the ongoing development of Xalan.</p>
</s3>

<anchor name="xml4c"/>     
&status-c;   

<anchor name="contact"/>
<s3 title="Getting in Touch">
<p>Your feedback is more than welcome. Offers of help are even more so! Perhaps you would like to contribute to the ongoing development, testing, or documentation of &xslt4c;.</p> 
<p>Please email your comments, questions, suggestions, bug reports, and offers to help to <human-resource-ref idref="xalandev"/>.</p>
</s3>

<anchor name="history"/>
<s3 title="Cumulative history of software changes">
<p>The following sections list the changes in each release since &xslt4c; version 0.40.0.</p>
&history-c;
</s3> 
  
</s2>

</s1>
