<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/document.dtd"[
<!ENTITY done-c SYSTEM "DONE">
<!ENTITY status-c SYSTEM "STATUS">
<!ENTITY history-c SYSTEM "history.xml">]>

<!--
 * Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->
<s1 title="What's New in this Release">
<p>Release notes for &xslt4c-current;</p>
 <ul>
  <li><link anchor="status">Status</link></li>
  <li><link anchor="contact">Getting in touch</link></li>
  <li><link anchor="history">History of software changes</link></li>  
 </ul>
<anchor name="status"/>
<s2 title="Status">
  <ul>
    <li><link anchor="done">Changes for &xslt4c; version 1.9</link></li>
    <li><link anchor="bugs">Bug reporting</link></li>    
    <li><link anchor="xml4c">Version of &xml4c; to use</link></li>
    <li><link anchor="to-do">To-do tasks for future &xslt4c; releases</link></li>
  </ul>

<anchor name="done"/>
<s3 title="Changes for &xslt4c; version 1.9">
<p>Major updates since version 1.8 include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Pluggable Memory Management.  This feature allows applications to maintain precise control over memory allocations.  This 
      will allow users, with knowledge of their application's characteristics, to provide a more efficient allocation method 
      than the general purpose procedures provided by the system.</li>
  <li>Improved performance on stylesheet execution.  Because the current implementation relies on function recursion, certain
      stylesheets/input documents may cause the program stack to overflow and cause the application to fail.  It also may 
      inhibit executing stylesheets that are heavily dependent on recursive functions.  This feature will prevent these types 
      of failure. </li>
  <li>Upgrade from Xerces-C 2.5 to Xerces-C 2.6. </li>
  <li><link anchor="bugfixes">Bugs fixed in this release</link>.</li>
 </ul>  
</s3>  

<anchor name="bugfixes"/>
<s2 title="Bugs Fixed in this Release">
<p>The bugs fixed in this release include:</p>
<ul>
   <li>Fixed bug in binary operators. Failed to detect a missing term. (XPathProcessorImpl.cpp, XPathProcessorImpl.hpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed threadsafe issues in XalanEXSLTDateTime. (Bugzilla 28818) (XalanEXSLTDateTime.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed incorrect linefeed serialization after an XML declaration. (various files) </li>
   <li>Fixed behaviour of xsl:number to conform to XSLT erratum E24 (See http://www.w3.org/1999/11/REC-xslt-19991116-errata/). 
       (ElemNumber.cpp) </li>
   <li>Fixed memory corruption when encoding of the output is set to UTF-16. (Jira XALANC-438) (FormatterToXML_UTF16.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed InvalidStackContextException exception. endExecuteChildren() not being called. (ElemVariable.cpp, ElemWithParam.cpp) </li>
   <li>Fixed problem with global variables. (Bugzilla 27959) (VariablesStack.cpp) </li>
   <li>Fixed bug in capacity(). (XalanDOMString.hpp) </li>
   <li>Fixed bug in creation/deletion of key maps (key-value/node-list pairs) for tree-fragments. (Jira XALANC-425) 
       (StylesheetExecutionContextDefault.cpp) </li>
   <li>Fixed leakage of DOMStringPrintWriter instances. (StylesheetExecutionContextDefault.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in reset(). (StylesheetExecutionContextDefault.hpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in with the omit-xml-declaration attribute (xsl:output). (Bugzilla 29545) (FormatterToXMLBase.cpp)</li>
   <li>Calling a named template should not change the current template rule. (Bugzilla 27841) (various files)</li>
   <li>Fixed conflict resolution problem for unique attributes with the same qname. (Bugzilla 23955) (ElemAttribute.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed problem with out-of-scope xsl:variable's not being detected in certain circumstances. 
      (Bugzilla 29079) (ElemTemplateElement.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in exslt extension function date-time().  Wrong GMT offsets were being reported. 
      (Bugzilla 27365) (XalanEXSLTDateTime.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in XalanSourceTreeElementNA::getLocalName(). (Bugzilla 27982) (XalanSourceTreeElementNA.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in XalanTransformer::initialize() (Bugzilla 22350)  (XalanTransformer.cpp)</li>
   <li>Cleaned up whitespace stripping. Fixed bug with whitespace stripping and xsl:copy-of. (various files)</li>
   <li>Cleaned up embedded string literals and unnecessary copies. (various files)</li>  
   <li>Removed createDOMFactory() call, because we cannot truly support it. (XMLParserLiaison.hpp)</li>
   <li>Cleaned up minor spelling problems in XalanMsg_en_US.xlf. (Bugzilla 30750)</li>
   <li>Fixed compilation problems with cygwin, gcc 2.95.3 and Tru64.</li>
   <li>Fixed compilation problems with HP aCC v3.52. (Bugzilla 29983)</li>
   <li>Fixed compilation problem with gcc 3.4.0 (Jira XALANC-423)</li>   
   <li>Fixed Win64 linkage problem.  Do not link with the Intel's default libmmd.lib library.</li>
   <li>Fixed problem with INSTALL_{PROGRAM->DATA}. (Bugzilla 27404)</li>
   <li>Build fails if no ICUROOT is set. (Jira XALANC-422)</li>
   <li>FreeBSD configure changes for threading.  (Bugzilla 27406)</li>
   <li>Update runConfigure to include new HP Itanium platform (hp-11-ia64). (Bugzilla 28452)</li>
   <li>Fixed AIX packaging bug. ICU on AIX now produces archives instead of shared objects.</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in CompileStylesheet.dsp that prevented building the sample on Win32.</li>
   <li>Fixed spelling errors in usagepatterns.xml. (JIRA XALANC-428)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug involving exporting the Harness symbols in Win64 with ICU dll. (AllInOneWithICU.dsp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug to enable build on HP-UX/aCC - workaround symbol length limit.(Makefile.incl.in)</li>
   <li>Enabled build of PerfT/Performance tests as well as direct conf's intermediate build files to the correct location. (conf.vcproj, PerfT.vcproj, perf.vcproj)</li>
   <li>Added status value error checking and included an example of the ICU memory management feature by altering SimpleTransform sample.</li>
   <li>Updated Makefiles for zOS build (Makefile.in)</li>
   <li>Corrected initialization of XalanMap with XalanVector as a data value</li>
   <li>Modified XalanFileUtility.cpp by commenting out system call to bring up results html file in a browser.</li>
   <li>Improved XalanMap implementation (XalanMap.hpp)</li>
   <li>Right configuation for XalanVector , preventing memory allocation from the global heap (XalanMap.hpp)</li>
   <li>Avoid trying to resolve against a base URI which is relative. (XalanParsedURI.cpp)</li>
   <li>Simplified boolean expressions. (XalanParsedURI.hpp)</li>
   <li>Use std::vector instead of XalanVector, since we cannot use the former until Xerces-C is initialized. (process.cpp) </li>
   <li>Added code to ensured that ICU cleanup code is called. (process.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug for providing backward API compatibility for Formatter* classes. (various files)</li>
   <li>Fixed build bug for Solaris platform. (XPath.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug in iterative stylesheet processing.  Execution was corrupted if &lt;xsl:for-each&gt; contained a single &lt;xsl:call-template&gt; and the invoked template was not the last template in the stylesheet. (ElemForEach.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug where incorrect template was chosen when checking for conflicts. (Stylesheet.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug to set proper document source URI (fixes testXSLT when inputs are specified with a relative path).  (XSLTEngineImpl.cpp)</li>
   <li>Fixed bug where XML identifier was getting clobbered. (XSLTEngineImpl.cpp)</li>
   <li>Provided an option to pool all text node strings. (various files) </li>
   <li>Updated docs in anticipation of 1.9 release (various files)</li>
</ul>
</s2>

<anchor name="bugs"/>
<s3 title="Bug reporting">
<p>All known &xslt4c; bugs are listed in <resource-ref idref="jira"/>. For a list of open bugs with links to each bug
   report, see <resource-ref idref="buglist"/>. If you find a new bug, please enter a XalanC bug report in this
   database.</p>
<note>Before you can enter your first bug report, you must submit your email address to JIRA and receive a password.</note> 
<p>We strongly encourage you write patches for problems you find and submit them to
   xalan-dev@xml.apache.org. We review the patches we receive to make sure they do not break something else, and (assuming they 
   do not) include them in our next release. In the interest of fixing bugs, adding enhancements, and addressing outstanding design
   issues, we sincerely want (and need!) your active participation in the ongoing development of Xalan.</p>
</s3>

<anchor name="xml4c"/>     
&status-c;     
</s2>

</s1>
