<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/faqs.dtd">

<faqs title="Frequently asked questions">

  <faq title="Where do I go to learn about XSLT">  
    <q>Where do I go to learn about XSLT?</q>
    
    <a><p>The definitive sources are the W3C XSLT and XPath recommendations: <resource-ref idref="XSLT"/> and 
    <resource-ref idref="XPath"/>.</p>
    <p>For general questions not specific to &xslt4c;, see Dave Pawson's <resource-ref idref="dpawsonxslfaq"/> and Michael Kay's 
    <jump href="http://www.wrox.com/Consumer/Store/Details.asp?ISBN=1861003129">XSLT Programmer's Reference</jump>.</p>
    <p>For a brief listing of tutorials, discussion forums, and other materials, see <link idref="overview"
     anchor="uptospeed">Getting up to speed with XSLT</link>.</p></a>
  </faq>
  
<faq title="Asking questions"><q>Where can I ask a question?</q>

<a><p>For generic questions about XSL stylesheets and transformations, use the <jump href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/xsl/xsl-list/">XSL-List -- Open Forum on XSL</jump> hosted by Mulberry Technologies. There is an archive that can be searched as well. Please review the archive before posting a new question.</p>

<p>For specific questions on &xslt4c;, see xalan-c-users@xml.apache.org and xalan-dev@xml.apache.org on <jump href="http://archive.covalent.net/">http://archive.covalent.net/</jump>. To subscribe to these mailing lists, see <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">Mailing Lists</jump>. Again, please review the archives before posting a new question.</p>
</a>
</faq>

<faq title="What is &xml4c;?">
<q>What is &xml4c; and why do I need it?</q>

<a><p>&xml4c; is a validating XML parser written in a portable subset of C++. &xml4c; makes it easy to give your application the ability to read and write XML data. Like &xslt4c;, &xml4c; is available from the Apache XML site:  http://xml.apache.org/xerces-c/index.html</p><!--xml4cNote--></a>
</faq>
  

  <faq title="Which version of Xerces should I be using?">  
    <q>Which version of Xerces should I be using?</q>
    
    <a><p>The &xslt4c; release notes includes information about the &xml4c; release with which the &xslt4c; release has been coordinated and tested. See <link idref="readme" anchor="status">Status</link></p><!--xml4cNote--></a>
  </faq>
  
<faq title="Problems with samples in Windows">
<q>I have encountered problem executing the &xslt4c; sample applications after rebuilding them under Win32 Environment (Windows NT 4.0, SP3).
 When I tried to execute the sample, I receive the error message "Debug Assertion Failed! ...  Expression: _BLOCK_TYPE_IS_VALID(pHead->nBlockUse)".</q>

<a><p>You may be mixing debug and release versions of executables and libraries. In other words, if you are compiling the sample for debug, then you should link with the debug version of the &xslt4c; and &xml4c; libraries and run with the debug version of the dynamic link libraries.</p>
<p>You must also make sure your application is linking with the Debug multithreaded DLL run-time library or the Multithreaded DLL run-time library.  To check this setting do the following in Visual C++:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Select Settings from the Project menu.<br/><br/></li>
  <li>Click the C/C++ tab.<br/><br/></li>
  <li>In the Category drop-down list, select Code Generation.<br/><br/></li>
  <li>In the Use run-time library drop-down list, select Multithreaded DLL for the Win32 Release configuration, or select Debug Multithreaded DLL for the Win32 Debug configuration.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have changed this setting, you must rebuild your project.</p>
<anchor name="build"/><p/></a>
</faq>

<faq title="Building on Windows">
<q>What do I need to rebuild &xslt4c; on Windows?</q>

<a><p>To build &xslt4c; on Windows, you need &xml4c; and MS Visual C++ 6.0 installed with Service Pack 3 for Visual C++ and Visual Studio. You should also apply the bug fixes for the C++ standard library that shipped with Visual C++ 6.0. These fixes are available from the Dinkumware site: <jump href="http://www.dinkumware.com/vc_fixes.html">http://www.dinkumware.com/vc_fixes.html</jump>.</p>
<p>If you do not want to apply the Dinkumware patches, or you are using a different Service Pack, you must rebuild all of the Xerces and Xalan binaries.</p>
<p>For more details, see <link idref="readme" anchor="win32">Steps for doing a Windows build</link>.</p></a>
</faq>

<faq title="Building on UNIX">
<q>What do I need to rebuild &xslt4c; on UNIX?</q>

<a><p>To build &xslt4c; on supported UNIX platforms, you need &xml4c;, the GNU make utility, and a supported C++ compilers (see the table below).</p>
<p>For more details see: http://xml.apache.org/xalan-c/readme.html#unix</p>
     <table>
       <tr>
         <th>Platform - Operating System</th>
         <th>Compilers</th>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>AIX 4.3</td>
         <td>IBM C and C++ for AIX 5.02</td>
      </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>Solaris 2.6</td>
         <td>Sun Workshop 6 update 2</td>
      </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>HP/UX 11.0</td>
         <td>aCC A.03.33</td>
      </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>Red Hat Linux 7.2</td>
         <td>gcc 3.1</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
 <p>For more details see: <link idref="readme" anchor="unix">Steps for doing a UNIX build</link>.</p>
</a></faq>

<faq title="Make errors on UNIX platforms">
<q>I get errors in the Makefile when running the make utility.  What's wrong?</q>

<a><p>You must use the GNU make utility.  Other make utilities may not work with the Xalan Makefile</p>
</faq>

<faq title="ICU">
<q>What is ICU and why do I need it?</q>

<a><p>The International Components for Unicode(ICU) is a C and C++ library that provides robust and full-featured Unicode support on a wide variety of platforms. &xslt4c; uses the ICU to extend support for encoding, number formatting, and sorting.</p> 
<p>The ICU is available for download from <jump href="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/icu/project/index.html">http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/icu/project/index.html</jump>.</p>
<p>This release of Xalan was tested with ICU 2.2.</p>
<p>For more details see: <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="icu">Using the International Components for Unicode (ICU)</link>.</p><!--icuNote--><anchor name="gnutar"/><p/></a>
</faq>

   <faq title="A tar checksum error on Solaris">
      <q>I am getting a tar checksum error on Solaris. What's the problem?</q>
      <a>
         <p>The Solaris tar utility you are using does not properly handle files with long pathnames.
         You must use GNU tar (gtar), which handles arbitrarily long pathnames
            and is freely available on every platform on which &xslt4c; is
            supported.  If you don't already have GNU tar installed on your system,
            you can obtain it from the Free Software Foundation
            <jump href="http://www.gnu.org/software/tar/tar.html">
            http://www.gnu.org/software/tar/tar.html</jump>.  For additional
            background information on this problem, see the online manual
            <jump href="http://www.gnu.org/manual/tar/html_node/tar_117.html#SEC112">
            GNU tar and POSIX tar </jump> for the utility.
         </p>
      </a>
   </faq>
   
<faq title="&xslt4c; in Apache">
<q>Is it possible to run &xslt4c; from an Apache server?</q>

<a><p>A simple Apache module called <link idref="samples" anchor="apachemodulexslt">ApacheModuleXSLT</link> is provided as a sample. It demonstrates how to integrate &xslt4c; with Apache.</p></a>
</faq>

    
  <faq title="Is &xslt4c; thread-safe?">
  
    <q>Is &xslt4c; thread-safe?</q>
       
    <a>
    <p>Instances of XalanTransformer are not thread-safe; each thread should use its own instance.</p>
    <p>In order to support very efficient use in multi-threaded applications, &xslt4c; is designed to avoid synchronization as much as
     possible. Each thread of execution is required to have its own set of "support" objects that contain the state of the
     transformation.  Accordingly, no synchronization is required when multiple threads are executing.</p>
     
     <p>Parsed ("compiled") stylesheets (see <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="compiled">Compiling stylesheets</link>) and parsed
      source documents may be freely shared by multiple threads of execution without worrying
      about providing synchronized access to them. The <em>only</em> exception to this rule: You use XercesParserLiaison to parse a
      document after calling XercesParserLiaison::setBuildBridgeNodes(false) or XercesParserLiaison::setThreadSafe(false). In this case,
      the document <em>cannot</em> be shared by multiple threads of execution. For reasons of performance, we do not recommend the use of
      XercesParserLiaison, so this should not be an issue for most applications.</p>
      
     <p>All other objects in &xslt4c; are <em>not</em> thread-safe. Each thread must have its own instance of each object.</p>
     
     <p>See the <link idref="samples" anchor="threadsafe">ThreadSafe</link> sample program for more information.</p></a>
  </faq>
   
  <faq title="What can I do to speed up transformations?">
  
    <q>What can I do to speed up transformations?</q>
    
    <a><p>To maximize performance, here are some suggestions for you to keep in mind as you set up your applications:</p><ul>
    <li>Use a compiled stylesheet when you expect to use the stylesheet more than once.<br/><br/></li>     
    <li>Set up your stylesheets to function efficiently.<br/><br/></li>
       <ul>
         <li>Don't use "//" (descendant axes) patterns near the root of a large document.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>Use xsl:key elements and the key() function as an efficient way to retrieve node sets.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>Where possible, use pattern matching rather than xsl:if or xsl:when statements.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>xsl:for-each is fast because it does not require pattern matching.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>Keep in mind that xsl:sort prevents incremental processing.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>When you create variables, &lt;xsl:variable name="fooElem" select="foo"/&gt; is usually faster than
         &lt;xsl:variable name="fooElem"&gt;&lt;xsl:value-of-select="foo"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:variable&gt;.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>Be careful using the last() function.<br/><br/></li>
         <li>The use of index predicates within match patterns can be expensive.<br/><br/></li>
       </ul>
    </ul></a>
  </faq>

  	<faq title="Stylesheet validation">
		<q>Can I validate an XSL stylesheet?</q>
		<a>
      <p>An XSL stylesheet is an XML document, so it can have a DOCTYPE and be subject to validation, but you probably will have
      to write a custom DTD for the purpose.</p>
      <p>The XSLT Recommendation includes a <jump href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt#dtd">DTD Fragment 
      for XSL Stylesheets</jump> with some indications of what you need to do to create a complete DTD for a given
      stylesheet. Keep in mind that stylesheets can include literal result elements and produce output that is not valid
      XML.</p>
      <p>You can use the xsl:stylesheet doctype defined in xsl-html40s.dtd for stylesheets that generate HTML.</p>
		</a>
	</faq>
    
        <faq title="What does the XalanDOMException HIERARCHY_REQUEST_ERR mean?">
      <q>What does the XalanDOMException HIERARCHY_REQUEST_ERR mean?</q>
      <a>
        <p>It means that an attempt was made to add a node to a DOM that would create
          an invalid structure.  For example, text nodes are not allowed as children
          of the document node.</p>

          <p>This is a common error when attempting to transform to DOM.
          Source documents and stylesheets that might produce valid serialized XML
          might not produce value DOM.  The usual suspect is text nodes being
          generated before the document element is generated.</p>
          <p>If you think you have seen this error because of a bug in Xalan-C++'s source tree
          implementation, please post a bug report on Bugzilla, and attach a minimal source document 
          and stylesheet that produce the problem to the bug report.</p>
      </a>
    </faq>

    
<faq title="Patches">
<q>Who do I submit patches to?</q>
<a><p>Your contributions are much appreciated! Please e-mail your patches to <human-resource-ref idref="xalandev"/>.</p></a>
</faq>
    
</faqs>
