<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>  
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/document.dtd">

<s1 title="Getting Started with Xalan-C++">
<ul>
<li><link anchor="download">Downloading what you need</link></li>
<li><link anchor="path">Setting up the path/library path</link></li>
<li><link anchor="samples">Trying out the samples</link></li>
<li><link anchor="commandline">Performing your own transformations from the command line</link></li>
<li><link anchor="apps">Setting up your own XSLT applications</link></li>
</ul>
<anchor name="download"/>
<s2 title="Downloading what you need">
<p>For &xslt4c-current;, we are distributing a Windows32 Visual C++ build and 5 UNIX builds with makefiles: a Red Hat Linux GNU build, an AIX xlC build, an HP-UX 11 aCC 32-bit build, an HP-UX 11 aCC 64-bit build, and a Solaris build. 
Please contact us at <human-resource-ref idref="xalandev"/> if you would like to help provide builds for other platforms.</p>
<p>If you do not already have it, you must also download the &xml4c; 2.1.0 build as indicated below.</p> 
<note>The Xalan distribution files are in <resource-ref idref="xslt4c-distdir"/>. The Xerces distribution files are in <resource-ref idref="xml4c-distdir"/>.</note>
   <table>
     <tr>
       <th>Xalan distribution files</th>
       <th>Xerces distribution files</th>
       <th>Platform</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-win32.zip</td>
       <td>&xml4c-dist;-win32.zip</td>
       <td>Windows32</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-linux.tar.gz</td>
       <td>&xml4c-linuxdist;</td>
       <td>Redhat Linux 7.2</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-aix.tar.gz</td>
       <td>&xml4c-aixdist;</td>
       <td>AIX 4.3</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-solaris.tar.gz</td>
       <td>&xml4c-solarisdist;</td>
       <td>Solaris 2.6</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-hp-ux.tar.gz</td>
       <td>&xml4c-hpdist;</td>
       <td>HP-UX 11.0 (32 bit)</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>&xslt4c-dist;-hp-ux-64.tar.gz</td>
       <td>&xml4c-hp64dist;</td>
       <td>HP-UX 11.0 (64 bit)</td>
    </tr>    
  </table>
  <p>The Windows32 distribution was built with MSVC 6.0 SP3 and <jump href="http://www.dinkumware.com/vc_fixes.html">Dinkumware C++ library fixes</jump>. The Red Hat Linux 7.2 32-bit distribution was built with gcc 3.1. The AIX 4.3 32-bit distribution was built with IBM C and C++ for AIX 5.02. The Solaris 2.6 32-bit distribution was built with Sun Workshop 6 update 2. 
The HP-UX 11 32-bit and 64-bit distributions were built with aCC A.03.33.</p>
<note>Use GNU tar to untar the Solaris distribution file; see <link idref="faq" anchor="gnutar">A tar checksum error on Solaris </link>.</note>
<p>This release also includes alpha support for building 64-bit Solaris and AIX binaries. See <link idref="readme" anchor="64bit">building 64-bit binaries</link>.</p>
<anchor name="xalandists"/>

<p>If you want to take advantage of the support for number formatting, sorting, and encoding the ICU provides, you should also download and install the <resource-ref idref="icu"/>; see <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="icu">Using the ICU</link>,</p>
</s2><anchor name="path"/>
<s2 title="Setting up the path/library path">
<ul>
  <li><link anchor="windowspath">For Windows</link></li>
  <li><link anchor="unixpath">For UNIX</link></li>  
</ul><anchor name="windowspath"/>
<s3 title="For Windows">
<p>To use the Windows distribution, you must place the Xalan executables and the Xalan and Xerces libraries on the path:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan\c\Build\Win32\VC6\Release and &xml4c-dist;-win32\bin on the path.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Visual C++ Xalan project included with the Windows release knows the relative paths to the Xalan headers and libraries, but it does not know where you have unzipped the Xerces distribution. If you plan to use Visual C++ to build Xalan applications or <link idref="readme" anchor="jar">rebuild Xalan</link>, you must also provide Visual C++ with access to the Xerces headers and libraries.</p> 
<p>Use the Visual C++ Tools menu to open the Options dialog box, go to the Directories tab, and do the following:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Add the path to &xml4c-dist;-win32\include to the list of directories of Include files (see the figure below).</li>
      <li>Add the path to &xml4c-dist;-win32\lib to the list of directories of Library files (see the figure below).</li></ul>
<p><img src="options-include.gif"/></p>

</s3><anchor name="unixpath"/>
<s3 title="For UNIX">
<p>To use one of the UNIX distributions, you must place the Xalan executable on the path, and the Xalan and Xerces libraries on the library path.</p>
<p>For the &xslt4c; Linux distribution:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/bin on the path (PATH).</li>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/lib and &xml4c-linuxdist;/lib on the library path (LD_LIBRARY_PATH), or copy the shared libraries to /usr/lib.</li>
</ul>
<p>For the &xslt4c; AIX distribution:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/bin on the path (PATH).</li>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/lib and &xml4c-aixdist;/lib on the library path (LIBPATH), or copy the shared libraries to /usr/lib.</li>
</ul>
<p>For the &xslt4c; HP-UX 11 32-bit distribution:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/bin on the path (PATH).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/lib and &xml4c-hpdist;/lib on the library path (SHLIB_PATH), or copy the shared libraries to /usr/lib.</li>
</ul>
<p>For the &xslt4c; HP-UX 11 64-bit distribution:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/bin on the path (PATH).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/lib and &xml4c-hp64dist;/lib on the library path (SHLIB_PATH), or copy the shared libraries to /usr/lib.</li>
</ul>
<p>For the &xslt4c; Solaris distribution:</p>
<ul>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/bin on the path (PATH).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Put xml-xalan/c/lib and &xml4c-linuxdist;/lib on the library path (LD_LIBRARY_PATH), or copy the shared libraries to /usr/lib.</li>
</ul>
</s3>
</s2><anchor name="samples"/>
<s2 title="Trying out the samples">
<p>The &xslt4c; distribution includes a number of basic sample applications. We have precompiled these samples for you so they are ready to run, and you can review the source files to see just how they work. </p>
<p>To run the samples, do the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Set up your path (see above). In the Windows32 distribution, the sample executables are in
xml-xalan\c\Build\Win32\VC6\Release. In the UNIX distributions, the executables are in xml-xalan/c/bin.</li>
<li>Go to the samples subdirectory containing the sample.</li>
<li>Run the sample from the command line (in Windows, use the DOS shell).</li>
<li>Examine the application source files.</li>
</ol>
<p>For example, go to the SimpleTransform subdirectory and issue the following command:</p>
<p><code>SimpleTransform</code></p>
<p>SimpleTransform uses the foo.xsl stylesheet to transform foo.xml, and writes the transformation result to foo.out. To see how the example works, examine the source files: foo.xml, foo.xsl, foo.out, and SimpleTransform.cpp.</p>
<p>For more information about the samples, see <link idref="samples">&xslt4c; Samples</link>.</p>
</s2><anchor name="commandline"/>
<s2 title="Performing your own transformations from the command line">
<p>The Xalan executable lets you perform transformations from the command line. The command line for 
most standard transformations is as follows:</p>
<p><code>Xalan -o <ref>outputfile</ref> <ref>xmlSource</ref> <ref>stylesheet</ref></code></p>
<p>where <ref>xmlSource</ref> is the XML source file name, <ref>stylesheet</ref> is the XSL stylesheet file name, and <ref>outputfile</ref> is the output file name.</p>
<p>If you want the output to be displayed on the screen, simply omit the -o flag and <ref>outputfile</ref>.</p>
<p>You can use this utility to try out XSL stylesheets you have written, to make sure they do what you expect with the XML source files they are designed to transform. The utility provides useful messages if the source file or stylesheet is not well formed. If you include a DOCTYPE statement or Schema hint in your XML source files and include the -v flag on the command line, the utility will also let you know whether the XML document is valid (conforms to that DOCTYPE or Schema). For more information, see <link idref="commandline">Command-Line Utility</link>.</p>
</s2><anchor name="apps"/>
<s2 title="Setting up your own XSLT applications">
<p>You can start by using your own XML source files and XSL stylesheets with the sample applications, which illustrate a number of usage patterns. For more information on setting up applications, see <link idref="usagepatterns">Basic Usage Patterns</link>.</p>
</s2>
</s1>