<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>  
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "sbk:/style/dtd/document.dtd">

<s1 title="Getting Started with Xalan-C++">
<ul>
<li><link anchor="download">Downloading what you need</link></li>
<li><link anchor="path">Setting up the system path</link></li>
<li><link anchor="samples">Trying out the samples</link></li>
<li><link anchor="commandline">Performing your own transformations from the command line</link></li>
<li><link anchor="apps">Setting up your own XSLT applications</link></li>
</ul>
<anchor name="download"/>
<s2 title="Downloading what you need">
<p>For &xslt4c-current;, we are distributing a Windows32 Visual C++ build, a Red Hat Linux GNU build, and an AIX xlC_r build. Please contact us at <human-resource-ref idref="xalandev"/> if you would like to help provide builds for other platforms.</p>
<s3 title="&xslt4c; Distributions">
<p><img src="xalan-cdist.gif" alt="xalan-cdist.gif"/></p>
</s3>
<p>For the Windows32 build, download <resource-ref idref="xslt4c-win32-download"/>.</p>
<p>For the Linux build, download <resource-ref idref="xslt4c-linux-download"/></p>
<p>For the AIX build, download <resource-ref idref="xslt4c-aix-download"/></p>
<p>Each distribution contains all you need to run the Xalan command-line utility for performing transformations. To build your own applications, you also need a compatible &xml4c; binary distribution. If you want to take advantage of the support for number formatting, sorting, and encoding the ICU provides, you should also download and install the <resource-ref idref="icu"/>; see <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="icu">Using the ICU</link>,</p>
<s3 title="What you need to run the Xalan command-line utility">
<p>To run the Xalan executable for performing transformations, you need the following:</p>
<p><em>Windows32</em></p>
<ul>
<li>The executable: TestXSLT.exe</li>
<li>The Xalan-C++ dynamic link libraries: &xslt4c-windlls;</li>
<li>The Xerces-C++ dynamic link library: &xml4c-windll;</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Linux</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>The executable: TestXSLT</li>
  <li>The Xalan-C++ shared library: &xslt4c-linuxlib;</li>
  <li>The Xerces-C++ shared library: &xml4c-linuxlib;</li>
</ul>
<p><em>AIX</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>The executable: TestXSLT</li>
  <li>The Xalan-C++ load library: &xslt4c-aixlib;</li>
  <li>The Xerces-C++ load library: &xml4c-aixlib;</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want to enable ICU support for the command-line utility, you must build the ICU and rebuild TestXSLT. See <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="icu">Using the ICU</link> and <link idref="commandline" anchor="icu">Enabling ICU support for TestXSLT</link>.</p>
<p>For information about using the command-line utility, see <link idref="commandline">Command-Line Utility</link>.</p>
</s3>
<s3 title="What you need to build applications">
<p>To build your own applications with Xalan and Xerces, you also need need the
Xalan-C++ and Xerces-C++ header (.hpp) files and (for Windows) the &xslt4c; and &xml4c; libraries (.lib files).</p>
<p>The Xalan-C++ header files are in the src directory tree in both distributions.</p> 
<p>In the Windows32 distribution (built with Microsoft&reg; Visual C++&reg; 6.0), the dlls and libraries are in the Build - Win32 -V6 - Release subdirectory.</p> 
<p>In the Linux distribution (built on Red Hat Linux 6.1 with a make file and the CNU C++ compiler), the shared object library is in the lib subdirectory.</p>
<p>In the AIX distribution (built with the make file and xlC_r), the load library is in the lib subdirectory.</p>
<p>To get the Xerces-C++ header and (for Windows) .lib files, download and expand the &xml4c; binary distribution for your platform from the <resource-ref idref="xml4c-distdir"/>. For information about which &xml4c; distribution has been tested with this &xslt4c; release, see <link idref="readme" anchor="status">Version of &xml4c; to use</link>.</p>
<p>For information about rebuilding &xslt4c;, see the <link idref="readme" anchor="build">Build notes</link>.</p>
</s3>
</s2><anchor name="path"/>
<s2 title="Setting up the path">
<p>For the Xalan-C++ Windows32 distribution, place xml-xalan\c\Build\Win32\VC6\Release on the path.</p>
<p>For the Xalan-C++ Linux distribution, place xml-xalan/c/bin and xml-xalan/c/lib on the shared library path (LD_LIBRARY_PATH for Red Hat Linux 6.1), or copy &xslt4c-linuxlib; to /usr/lib.</p>
<p>For the Xalan-C++ AIX distribution, place xml-xalan/c/bin and xml-xalan/c/lib on the load library path (LIB for xlC_r), or copy &xslt4c-aixlib; to /usr/lib.</p>

<p>If you do your own Xalan, ICU, and Xerces builds, be sure to include the directories that contain the libraries and the TextXSLT executable on your path.</p>
</s2><anchor name="samples"/>
<s2 title="Trying out the samples">
<p>The &xslt4c; distribution includes a number of basic sample applications. We have precompiled these samples for you so they are ready to run, and you can review the source files -- all of which are brief -- to see just how they work. </p>
<p>To run the samples, do the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Set up your path (see above). In the Windows32 distribution, the sample executables are in
xml-xalan\c\Build\Win32\VC6\Release. In the Linux and AIX distributions, the executables are in xml-xalan/c/bin.</li>
<li>Go to the samples subdirectory containing the sample (use the DOS shell in Windows).</li>
<li>Run the sample from the command line.</li>
<li>Examine the application source files.</li>
</ol>
<p>For example, go to the SimpleTransform subdirectory and issue the following command:</p>
<p><code>SimpleTransform</code></p>
<p>SimpleTransform uses the foo.xsl stylesheet to transform foo.xml, and writes the transformation result to foo.out. To see how the example works, examine the source files: foo.xml, foo.xsl, foo.out, and SimpleTransform.cpp.</p>
<p>For more information about the samples, see <link idref="samples">&xslt4c; Samples</link>.</p>
</s2><anchor name="commandline"/>
<s2 title="Performing your own transformations from the command line">
<p>TestXSLT provides a basic utility for performing transformations from the command line. The command line for 
most standard transformations is as follows:</p>
<p><code>TestXSLT -in <ref>xmlSource</ref> -xsl <ref>stylesheet</ref> -out <ref>outputfile</ref></code></p>
<p>where <ref>xmlSource</ref> is the XML source file name, <ref>stylesheet</ref> is the XSL stylesheet file name, and <ref>outputfile</ref> is the output file name.</p>
<p>If you want the output to be displayed on the screen, simply omit the -out flag and outputfile.</p>
<p>You can use this utility to try out XSL stylesheets you have written, to make sure they do what you expect with the XML source files they are designed to transform. The utility provides useful messages if the source file or stylesheet is not well formed. If you include a DOCTYPE statement in your XML source files and include the -validate flag on the command line, the utility will also let you know whether the XML document is valid (conforms to that DOCTYPE). For more information, see <link idref="commandline">Command-Line Utility</link>.</p>
</s2><anchor name="apps"/>
<s2 title="Setting up your own XSLT applications">
<p>You can start by using your own XML source files and XSL stylesheets with the sample applications, which illustrate a number of usage patterns. For more information on setting up applications, see <link idref="usagepatterns">Basic Usage Patterns</link>.</p>
</s2>
</s1>