<s3 title="Changes since &xslt4c; version 1.0">
<p>In addition to adding to the list of platforms on which &xslt4c; builds, our focus for this release has been on bug fixes, performance enhancements, 
and providing a simplified C++ and C API for performing standard transformations. Major updates since version 1.0 include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Added HP-UX 11 build.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Added Solaris build.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Greatly improved performance.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Improved conformance to the XSLT specification.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Simplified the C++ API and provided a C API for performing standard transformations with the <link idref="usagepatterns" 
anchor="xalantransformer">XalanTransformer</link> class and associated header files.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Added sample illustrating use of XalanTransformer and the new C++ API: 
    <link idref="samples" anchor="xalantransform">XalanTransform</link>.<br/><br/></li> 
<li>Added sample illustrating use of XalanTransformer, the new C API, and how to run &xslt4c; and perform transformations on an 
    Apache Web server: <link idref="samples" anchor="apachemodulexslt">ApacheModuleXSLT</link>.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Added the <link idref="samples" anchor="streamtransform">StreamTransform</link> sample.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Eliminated dependencies on non-public Xerces headers; accordingly can now build with the Xerces distribution.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed namespace mapping and inheritance problems.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed failure of &lt;copy-of ...&gt; to include CRLFs (if any) in the result.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed bug sorting in reverse document order based on position. <br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed &lt;xsl:number&gt; bug with use of letter-value="traditional" for "classical" Greek numbering.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed use of &lt;xsl:fallback&gt; within a top-level extension function.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed HTML output method bug. The &lt;HEAD&gt; element was not including a &lt;META&gt; tag with the encoding.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed bug using key() in match patterns to find descendants.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed bug using the id() function in complex match patterns.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problem outputting multiple single-character CDATA sections.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problem outputting whitespace characters.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problem transforming from a stream on UNIX platforms.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed a bug with the document() function, which was generating a syntax error if called in the following manner: document(<ref>string</ref>,/).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed named templates bug accepting global parameter when called with a parameter of the same name that the named template does not 
    recognize.</li>
</ul>
</s3>
<s3 title="Changes since &xslt4c; version 0.40.0">
<p>Major updates since version 0.40.0 include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Full support for namespace handling<br/><br/></li>
<li>Full implementation of the format-number() function and support for the decimal-format element<br/><br/></li>
<li>Integration with the <resource-ref idref="icu"/> for number formatting, sorting, and output encoding<br/><br/></li>
<li>Support for the exclude-result-prefixes attribute<br/><br/></li>
<li>Support for the output encoding attribute</li>
</ul>
</s3>
<s3 title="Changes since &xslt4c; version 0.30.0">
<p>Major updates since version 0.30.0 include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Permitting OS file names (as well as URLs) as command-line arguments with TestXSLT<br/><br/></li>
<li>Stricter compliance for HTML and XML output<br/><br/></li>
<li>Improved handling of relative URI's<br/><br/></li>
<li>Improved handling of Import and Include<br/><br/></li>
<li>Better namespace handling (although there are still problems here)<br/><br/></li>
<li>Support for Document() function<br/><br/></li>
<li>Support for XPath predicates<br/><br/></li>
<li>Better handling of parameters to stylesheet and templates<br/><br/></li>
<li>Full implementation of axes ( with the exception of namespace:: )<br/><br/></li>
</ul>
</s3>
	
